<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to both Houses of Parliament on the subject of their present proceedings against the Roman Catholicks of England.</title>
            <author>P. F.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54674</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831718</idno>
  <idno type="VID">36185</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248499422</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P19A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220299</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831718</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831718e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2051:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to both Houses of Parliament on the subject of their present proceedings against the Roman Catholicks of England.</title>
                  <author>P. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed and dated on p. 9: Paris, May 17/27. 1679. F. P.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Great Britain. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Catholics --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:36185:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36185:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO Both Houses of PARLIAMENT, On the subject of their present Proceedings against the Roman Catholicks of ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>May it please your Lordships, and You Gentlemen of the House of</hi> Commons.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Know the multitude of your Affairs, and therefore this Interru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption shall be no longer than seemeth necessary.</p>
            <p>I hope, that, since by permission of Authority <hi>OATES</hi> (the present Infamy of our Country) has taken on him the Office of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellor, or rather, Tutor to his Majesty, in the late Publication of his fantastick Depositions, it will not be needful to Apologize for this little admonitory Address to you. I confess, you now receive it from one single hand; but you must likewise be assured, that it is the Voice of the whole Christian World; which, because you stifle and suppress it in <hi>England</hi> by most severe Penalties, your best Friends are obliged to impart unto you from beyond-Sea.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36185:2"/>
            <p> You have raised a most violent PERSECUTION against <hi>Roman-Catholicks:</hi> You have thrown many Worthy Gentlemen into Jayles, and constrained others to quit their Native Country: You have taken away the Lives of several Honest Men, as well by strait and uncharitable Imprisonments, as by pretence of Justice, and form of Law: You have aspersed the clearest and most unblemished Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations with the foulest stains: You have dreadfully alarm'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd the People, and in a moment, chang'd a steddy and fruitful Peace into most restless and wasting Distractions: And all this under colour of an Hellish Plot, that was contrived, and is still carried on against his MAJESTIES Life: This you say is discovered to you by <hi>Titus Oates,</hi> and <hi>William Bedlow,</hi> and on their Testimony you have proceeded to so much Oppression and Blood. And all this while you are not ignorant what Reputation your Informers have, <hi>viz.</hi> that they are men, who by Cheats, Robberies, and Perjuries had long since lost all manner of Credit; and at this time were grown so indigent, that, perhaps, their Want had been a Temptation strong enough to better Consciences for such an advantagious Forgery. You know likewise, that as their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Falshoods and Perjuries were notorious, so even their present ones are manifest; and this not only by Clouds of Witnesses, both Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks and Protestants, which, notwithstanding the care taken to prevent it by banishing the one and frightning the other, do yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear against them; but also (besides other Absurdities) by plain Disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and palpable Contradictions in their own Evidence. You know how differently this pretended Information hath been given, and how often, <hi>Proteus</hi>-like, it hath changed its shape, being one thing before the Privy-Council, another before You, and a third before the Judges. You know how many gross Failings have been observed in it, not only by his MAJESTY, but by many of your selves. You know that the Best of your two Houses Voted the QUEEN innocent of such Crimes, as these two Villains were not afraid to swear against her; which was no otherwise in effect, than to declare the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation a Perjury. You know that the KING himself, who is the most concerned and has had the best opportunities of Examining this Mock-discovery, openly laughs at it. You know what Protestations of Innocence your humble Victims have all hitherto made at their Deaths,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36185:2"/>which (because you imagine few hearts hard enough to resist so mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and convincing a Proof) all your Narratives of their Executions conceal; and your ordinary Discourses find out such pitiful Evasions, that even I am ashamed to mention them: For, how can any one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Catholicks have Dispensations to attest Lies (even to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing themselves Protestants, as was said in <hi>Bury</hi>'s case) at their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the World, and being ready to appear before the dreadful and most exact Tribunal of Almighty God; when every body knows, that in all Ages since your Reformation some of them have lost their Employments, some their Estates, and others their Lives, for not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your Oaths and Tests, which such Dispensations, as you speak of, would have made most easie for them to do; and consequently have frustrated the effect of the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and sheltered them from those numerous and heavy Persecutions, which from time to time have been, and are at present most thickly showred upon them. Lastly, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but see how highly improbable it is, that there should have been an Army of 40 or 50 thousand Conspirators in readiness, and yet on this Discovery no other sign or evidence should appear of so great a thing but the bare Assertion of one or two infamous Rogues: And You your selves are so sensible hereof, that though on the account of a PLOT you <hi>Kill</hi> and <hi>Slay,</hi> yet you seem so far dissatisfied with any Evidence you have of it hitherto, as still to keep Fasts and days of Humiliation, that God would help you to discover it farther, and (what, I presume, you hold the most efficacious way of augmenting the number of your Discoverers) you are ready to free any Rascal out of the vilest Prison, who has wit enough to frame a little Tale on this subject; adding Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to his Liberty, and from beneath a Beggar raising him to the port and equipage of a Lord. What shall I say of all this? or rather, what does the whole world say of it; but that you seem at once to have lost all Prudence, Honesty, and Shame; there being nothing more imprudent, than thus by countenancing Perjury and Falshood, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the like (when occasion shall give way) against your selves; nothing more unjust than by form of justice to wrong the Innocent; and lastly, nothing more shameless than to act the most Ridiculous, as well as Barbarous Cruelties on the Theatre of the World, and in the view of all Mankind? Are you not afraid, that not only Christians for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36185:3"/>your Violence to Christianity, but even Turks and Infidels will unite against you as the Common Enemies of Humane Nature? And if your Pride lift you above those fears, are you not (at least) apprehensive of Divine Vengeance? Have you so soon forgot in how many Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and what strange Confusions our poor Nation was overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Heats far less than these? God Almighty, 'tis true, as strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly restored us back our Quiet and Tranquility: But when he does any such favour, as well to Nations as to particular Persons, he always adds a <hi>Noli amplius peccare,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sin no more, least a worse thing happen unto thee.</hi> We are beginning now to sin again, and, if we hold on the course, what can we expect, that this <hi>worse thing,</hi> which is to come upon us, should be, but even the total Ruine of our Country, and the Extirpation of our People? I confess that some of you are so ingenuous as to acknowledge, that the Accusations against CATHOLICKS are meer Calumnies, and improbable Falshoods: But, say you, we have need of them. What hath need of them, your Property, or your Religion? You will not say the first; because (supposing those dangers real, which some treacherously feign, and others as inconsiderately fear) you ought to have so much (not to say of Christians, but) of Gentlemen in you, as to use Forgeries as little for the preserving, as you would for the procuring an Estate: And then certainly you will easily grant me, that Religion must have less to do with any such thing; since for It to stand in need of Lies for its support and maintenance, is a strong evidence that it proceeded from the Father of them, and is it self also a most dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Imposture. But the Sufferers are Priests, or (at least) Papists, and though innocent of the Crimes objected to them, yet the Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the one being Treason, and the Religion of the other (if not in Law, yet in our opinion) as Criminal, we, for our parts, cannot think that they are wronged, when (though on another score) they are put to death: Such fancies as these are nothing else but Slights and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our subtil Adversary, wherewith he endeavours to quiet that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse of Conscience, which commonly is felt at the entrance of a Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness. My design is not to insist on the defence of our Religion: however give me leave in few words to propose to your consideration, how inconsistent it is with your Profession, and how unwarrantable by your own Principles to Persecute on that account. Pray reflect on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36185:3"/>this Dilemma, <hi>Either God Almighty has left us some living Guide, or Guides here on Earth for the interpreting Holy Writ, and the directing us in all other Points of Religion, and under pain of Damnation hath obliged us to follow the same: Or else he hath left this task to each of us in particular; imparting to us the Authority of being our own Guides, and freeing us from all necessity of submission to any other.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> will deny the former, not only because in order to their pretended Reformation they assumed a Liberty (as every body knows) most opposite to the Obligation of being guided by others, but also, because on the same account they were forced to assert that no Guides on Earth could be Infallible; and consequently there could be none, whom God had indispensably obliged us to Obey; it being impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that God should bind us to an Obedience, which might possibly (our Directors being Fallibe) engage us in error, and prove the cause of our eternal Damnation. It follows then that they must maintain the latter, <hi>viz. That</hi> (as Protestants commonly say) <hi>we are not bound to pin our Faith on anothers sleeve, but impower'd by God Almighty to guide our selves.</hi> Do you not perceive already, that in men of your Principles there is not the least excuse for Penalties on Religion? What are Dissenters in Religion guilty of, but of presuming to Guide themselves, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their own Consciences, which you confess is nothing else but what they are authorized by God himself to do? so that really, when you punish for Religion, you seem to deal no better with God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, than often you do with his Majesty, when even in his presence you correct that in his Ministers, which you know is done not only by his Approbation, but Command. I know not what arts you may use to limit Monarchy here on Earth, but, I hope, you will allow the King of Heaven to be Absolute. But after all, if you think that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion deserves Death, in God's name let them die for it: They own their Religion, and you may ease your selves of the expence of <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and cry out with <hi>Caiphas,</hi> what farther need have we of Witnesses? It is not lawful for you to murther their Reputations also, by traducing those who have no other Crime but their Faith, as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries and Traitors. And though I should grant you (contrary even to what your selves believe) that they have deserved all this, and whatever else they suffer, it does not follow that therefore it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for you to procure the punishment of Their Crimes, by committing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36185:4"/>others. I believe that many of you would scruple to take a false Oath against them, and am confident that none would declare it lawful to do so. Now, that other Opiate for Conscience of pleasing your selves that the whole weight of the Perjury lieth on <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> is as frivolous and weak an excuse, as what I have already mentioned. Are you not taught by Reason and the common Proverb, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealer is as bad as the Thief? whosoever buys stoln Goods, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be such, or conceals the Felon, involves himself in the theft. 'Tis true, the Knights of the Post are <hi>Oats</hi> and <hi>Bedlow;</hi> but you both purchase the <hi>false Oaths,</hi> and protect the <hi>Swearers.</hi> And I believe in the last day (forasmuch as concerns this matter) it will be more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable for <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> than for you; since, though your Crime seems to be the same with theirs, yet their extreme Want and most desperate Necessity was incomparably a greater Temptation, than any thing could be to you, who had no other Wants but what your own groundless Apprehensions framed to your selves. Nay, more than this, setting aside Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> you not only are those who countenance, but also who have drawn in the rest, laying baits for them, and with large Promises and as effectual Performances, even forcing them to come to your Lure; and this to such a degree, that, considering your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, a <hi>False Oath</hi> began to seem the most important piece of Service which we could do for our Countrey. Some of you say, 'tis true, you do not believe all what <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> tell you, <hi>viz.</hi> the Design of killing the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but you cry, there is somewhat in it. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you then, let not what is not in it be punisht, but what is: and that, when it appears by better Witnesses than <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> since either all is true that they swear, or nothing can be guessed, much less credited on their Testimony. Will you because they swear many great things falsly against us, the more easily believe the less? whereas, should they to your knowledge be guilty of Perjury but in one single point, you ought in Law and Conscience to admit no part of their Evidence, but absolutely to reject the whole: and if so, I presume it will be hard for you to tell me on what the belief of this <hi>somewhat,</hi> you speak of, is grounded: Unless you seriously consider thereof; and then, I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that you will perceive it to have no other foundations, save only that tough Prejudice against Roman Catholicks, wherein you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36185:4"/>have been bred, and that hidden Desire which is still nourished in your hearts of finding somewhat to reproach them with, and at the same time to appease those doubts which now and then perplex you about Religion, and to satisfie your Consciences how little need there is of embracing one so troublesome in its exercise, and (as matters go) so disadvantagious in its Profession, by representing it altogether as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy and impious, as it is inconvenient. They are, I say, your Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and your Interest, which strongly (though for the most part imperceptibly) byass and incline your minds to these rash judgments, causing you to make Conclusions, for which you have no reason, and shewing us how true that Maxim is (whereof you ought to be aware) <hi>viz. Quod volumus, facile credimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lords and Gentlemen, I trespass on your patience, and almost lose my own. I hope you will attribute to the irregularity of Grief, what excess soever this short Discourse may be guilty of: It grieves me here amongst our Neighbour Nations, to see our Credit (hardly yet whole of its late wounds) to bleed afresh, and with such violence, that already it seemeth past cure. It grieves me to see the SON almost fallen into those Hands, which so lately were embrewed in the Blood of the FATHER, and he himself (thanks to those <hi>Papists</hi> you now pretend to conspire against him) so narrowly escaped. And if the view of a Natural Father being in the like peril, caused a dumb Son to break his silence, what wonder is it if the imminent Dangers of our Common Father, yea, and of all our Brethren too, I mean, all his Subjects, should transport one who could speak before, somewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ordinary <hi>Decorum,</hi> and formalities of custom? The Substance is in so much hazard, that for the saving thereof, 'tis no great matter if a Ceremony be now and then omitted. He were not to be blamed, who to save a drowning Prince, should (without staying to make a Reverence) rudely pull him out of the Water by the arms.</p>
            <p>What shall I say more? I hope you will pardon Me, and look after Your selves: Be pleased to pause a little in the midst of this furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous career (though it be only to know, how far you can yet master your selves) and look, at least, whither it is that you are running so fast: Say to your selves, Let us consider a little what the whole World is now saying to us: Let us examine how sar these loud Excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36185:5"/>are reasonable: They who thus cry unto us, are men as well as our selves, and We may be mistaken as well as They. Let us then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider our own Interest and Security, the Honour of our Nation, our Allegiance to our Prince, and Duty to God Almighty, and see how far they are hurt by this monstrous Authority which two or three Rogues have gotten amongst us. Let us consider, whether, since the Pillories could not free us wholly from the inconvenience of Perjuries, an Encouragement of them will not increase their number to the ruine of our Commonwealth, and, most deservedly, of our selves in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. And why do we talk of Perjuries only, when there is neither Robbery, Sacriledge, Murther, Firing of Houses, nor any other Crime, which (according to the course we take) may not now be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely committed, since all these things, when ever they happen, are laid on the Papists: and though the Authors should have the ill fortune to be discovered, it is enough for them to say that some Papist set them on work: and they are so far from Punishment, that they are sure of being rewarded. Neither let it escape our thoughts, what it is to shed Innocent Blood; how deeply it stains; how loudly it cries; and how certainly 'tis heard. Let us also weigh, whither it was that the Ambition of a Few, and the foolish Credulity of Many hurried us by the late Rebellion? and whether or no (considering the posture of our Neighbours) the present Dissentions are not like to have a worse end. Let us in spight of Passion, Prejudice, and Popular Mistakes, set streight once more the Ballance of Justice; afford a free and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Hearing to both sides, weighing the Quality and Credibility, as well as Number of the Witnesses; boldly declare what we shall find on a sincere Enquiry; and in conclusion, act accordingly. Let those who are any ways moved, either by their own serious Reflection, or by this piece of Paper, (which perhaps one day will be produced against some with more Justice, than several Letters have of late been urged for the Evidence of a Conspiracy) take Courage. God will assist Those who are throughly resolved to be Honest. <hi>Darius</hi> threw inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Lions Den, for fear of those who said to him, <hi>Aut trade nobis Danielem, aut interficiemus te;</hi> and yet the next day (<hi>Daniel</hi>'s safety, most probably, having given him a greater confidence in God) he was not afraid to cast all Those into the same Den, with their Wives
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36185:5"/>and Children, who but the day before had terrified him, even to the wronging his Conscience, and destroying his best Friend; and they who then threatned him, and making him yield to an impiety, were consequently his Masters, as soon as now he became resolved to do Justice, dared not so much as to stir a finger against him.</p>
            <p>My Lords and Gentlemen, there is a certain strength in Honesty, which nothing can vanquish. Vertue has not any opposite but what is of the nature of the Devil, who is so easily overcome, that barely to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist him (as our Lord assures us) is to put him to flight. I beseech the same Lord to take away these evil and malignant Heats which are amongst you, and instead thereof to inspire you with a true Zeal for Religion, which so essentially requireth an exact Justice, that in truth 'tis nothing else: and therefore you find throughout the Scripture, that Justice, or (as you Translate) <hi>Righteousness,</hi> and the Service of God (<hi>viz.</hi> Religion) are terms equivalent. And if so, I hope the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestness that I have here shewn for Justice, which is so necessary a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification for one of God's <hi>Servants,</hi> will not cause me to seem the less,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most Faithful, and<lb/> most Humble</hi> Servant,<lb/> F. P.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi>
                  <date>May 17./27.<lb/> 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36185:6"/>
            <head>Postscript to the <hi>House of Commons.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce the Above-written, we are told of several strange Votes lately pass'd your House, wherein (whilst we thought that there could be nothing more wonderful than what we had already heard of You) we are made to see, that You, at least, can out-do your selves. One of your Votes (want of time compelling me to leave the rest for another oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity) is to this purpose,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That in case his MAJESTY (which God forbid) should come to any violent Death, you will (at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures) charge the Catholicks with the Treason, and revenge it on their whole Body in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>I beseech you, Gentlemen, what other Comment can be made of this Loyal Result of your Deliberations, but that in effect it is to secure any one, who is no Papist, to <hi>kill the King,</hi> by telling him before-hand that his Crime shall be laid on others? And the World is of opinion that (which God in his mercy prevent) by this VOTE some of you design nothing else, but to make the way easier to that abominable Fact, which you pretend to hinder; and also to prepare and teach the People how to resent it when 'tis done. I must confess that your VOTE would have been just enough, had none but Papists been capable of such a Villany; and had all the Protestants, quitting the claim of being <hi>Infallible</hi> in their <hi>General</hi> Body, made themselves <hi>Impeccable</hi> in their <hi>Particular</hi> Persons: or had it been necessary that whatsoever some one or more of Papists should Act, their whole Communion should have Contrived or Approved. But the case is quite different; we have seen by Experience, that in <hi>England</hi> the CATHOLICKS are so far from being the only Enemies to the Life of their King, that there was so great a multitude of <hi>those Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> amongst the Protestants, that they were strong enough to destroy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36185:6"/>it, when the opposite Party, though assisted by the Catholicks, was not able to defend it. Is it not an hard case, that poor Catholicks, who so unanimously and gallantly hazarded their Lives for That of their Prince, and are always ready to do the same, should now (right or wrong) be marked out for the only Sufferers, if ever (which God forbid) their Prince should happen to be killed, when there are still so many of the Old Regicides not only alive, but in Vogue and Authority; and so many more of their Sons who have double portions of their Fathers spirit? How many over-heated <hi>Presbyterians, Fifth-Monarchy-men,</hi> and other <hi>Fanaticks</hi> are there in <hi>England,</hi> who have Consciences fit enough for such an exploit, and with wresting a Text or two in Scripture, are able to perform ten times more than what you pretend the Papists do with Dispensations from the Pope? You may perceive by the late Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Murther of your Primate of <hi>Scotland,</hi> what regard they have to your most Sacred Dignities. And here give me leave to tell you, that 'tis more than highly probable that these Scottish Gospel-Bravoes were encouraged to such an horrid Fact by the present mode (which preceded your Vote) of casting all things of this nature on the Papists: And I know not but e're now they may have found a trick of throwing this also on their shoulders, in imitation of what was most inhumanely done on the accident of Justice <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Death, wherein they not only lost the benefit of a very good Friend, but were supposed most unreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, and without the least hope of other advantage to have murthered him themselves. Who can apprehend that the whole Body of Catholicks, who are in jeopardy of having their Throats cut on every less Murther that happens, should contrive or agree to such an Attempt against his MAJESTY; which, should it come to pass by unknown Authors, would (whatever you are pleased to VOTE) expose them to the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being torn in pieces by the Rabble? What is truly to be feared is, that some <hi>ex Vobis Ipsis</hi> infected with the Old Itch, as well of Plunder as of Domineering, should use means (especially should your claim to <hi>Omnipotence</hi> urge you to think of Dis-inheriting the HEIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>APPARENT) to Assasinate the King, and thereupon Massacre and Spoil the Papists, and then set up your Beloved Twins <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and a <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> wherein (if God interposeth not) you will effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually accomplish What you falsly pretend the Catholicks to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36185:7"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> The Murther of the King, the Change of the Government, and the Subversion of the Establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed Protestant Religion. And then perhaps many who were big with this Feigned PLOT, and expected great Exaltations from it, will find their mistake, and perceive that the young Viper has eaten through those Bowels wherein it was conceived. And amongst others, let my Lords the Bishops (some of whom on pretence of ensuring their Gospel, thought fit to preach up <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi>) consider that those Assassinates of <hi>Scotland</hi> are only the extreme parts (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Nails</hi> or <hi>Claws</hi>) of that greater Body, Who though they now <hi>Breakfast</hi> on US, will not fail to <hi>Dine</hi> on their LORDSHIPS: And so (that They may have somewhat to think of as well as the rest) fat themselves likewise for Those whom God in his just Anger shall appoint to devour them.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Discite Justitiam</hi> moniti—</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1679.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36185:7"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>